Unlabelled Class D artefacts.
Tosh, I need you to run a full check.
-Sure.
-JACK: Owen, you can help.
-Happy to.
-Adam, I know how much you love audits.
-It's gotta be done.
-If you could...
Go through the investigation reports,
find out when they might have come
through the rift.
-JACK: You okay with that?
-I have been for the last three years.
-You're late.
-Yes, Paris was lovely, thank you!
Who the hell is this?
Just 'cause that's what I said to you on
your first day.
Remember?
ADAM: Ow!
GWEN: You make a nice strong coffee.
Sorry, couldn't resist. Come here, you!
Good to see you.
Hey, Tosh, you're looking good.
TOSHIKO: Adam, what are you doing
with your personnel file?
Nothing, just finished updating details
of rift activity.
Any idea when this came through?
It's got a low meson energy reading.
No, I'll keep looking.
A year ago today.
-Our first kiss.
-You remembered.
You okay, Owen?
Yes, yes, yes, don't worry about me.
No, no, it's just...
Kissing in work, I wasn't expecting it.
We'll celebrate tonight.
(GROWLING)
Save it.
Jack?
-You okay?
-Yeah, fine.
-Did you miss me?
-Were you gone?
No!
(GWEN GIGGLING)
(SNARLING)
Just doing a quick check, we had rift
activity two days ago,
-but nothing seems to have come through.
-Apart from me!
What's that?
It's a screen cleaner.
I thought you might like it.
Do you like it?
Just what I need. A small rodent looking
at me while I work.
Think I'll call it Owen.
He's like a little puppy
bringing her sticks.
When's he gonna realise
he's got no chance?
Love's blind, apparently.
He's idolised her for years now.
Oh, leave him alone. I think it's sweet.
He's happy.
Oh, sorry! I didn't mean
to frighten you.
-How did you get in?
-With a key.
-This isn't funny.
-You stay back, all right? Stay back!
-Gwen, what's going on?
-How do you know my name? Huh?
I know how to use this.
Who are you and what do you want?
You know who I am.
Fine, if you won't tell me, fine.
You stay there. Don't you move.
Jack, yeah, someone's broken
into my flat. He had a key.
He knows my name.
-Yes, because I live here with you.
-Shut it! Shut it.
Yeah, can you hurry, Jack?
He's a nutter.
You have picked the wrong girl
to stalk, mate.
(BUZZER RINGING)
-Gwen...
-Stay there!
-Jack!
-Gwen, it's us!
In here, Jack!
-What's going on?
-You tell me.
Look, he's put photos of us up.
He must have done it
while I was at work.
He's deluded!
He keeps saying he's my boyfriend.
He is. It's Rhys.
-I've never seen him before in my life!
-You've been with him for years.
See!
-Give me the gun, Gwen.
-No! He grabbed me, Jack.
Who knows what he was going to do?
How can you say that?
What have you done to her?
-Nothing.
-Oh, come on!
I know what kind of sick games you play.
Pills that make you forget.
Is that what this is, yeah?
Are you phasing me out
so you can have her all to yourself?
-Stay away from him.
-We're engaged!
I bought you
the bloody ring you're wearing!
-Why don't you come with me to the Hub?
-Who the hell are you?
-He's one of us.
-We can check you over.
Jack will stay here
and take care of things.
Okay?
Don't let him go. If he comes
after me again, I'll kill him.
Trust me, I didn't do this,
but whatever's happened,
we'll put it right.
Right, well, no signs
of long term damage
as far as I can see.
Or alien intervention.
But I must be missing something.
I'm sorry, but it's a mystery to me
why you can't remember Rhys.
-Is this really necessary?
-She needs to remember.
(SIGHING)
Where did you meet?
At college, fancied her
from the moment I saw her.
(RHYS CHUCKLING)
Not just her looks, you know.
I mean, she is a looker.
Oh, I...
(RHYS GROANING)
JACK: Tell me about your first kiss.
RHYS: Erm, in the supermarket.
I was going to make her spag bol and...
Then I realised, didn't I?
It's got bloody garlic.
Can't kiss a girl with garlic breath.
No, we were in the queue.
Do you remember that?
Sort of. It's like I'm...
I'm seeing what he's saying, but
I don't remember how I felt.
Believe me when I tell you
that that is your fiancé.
Your memory's just playing
tricks on you, that's all. Okay?
Okay.
She starts to laugh,
she calls me Rhys the rant.
And then she kissed me,
right there in the queue.
And I thought then, Jack,
I thought, "I'm going to marry this
bloody mad woman even if it kills me."
TOSHIKO: Worked out
what that thing is yet?
No joy yet. But you should have a look
at the detail, Tosh, it's gorgeous.
Oh, let me get that.
Have you managed to open it yet?
No, sorry. I'm not doing very well,
am I?
It's gonna be a long night.
Yes, which is why I brought
some sandwiches!
One for you, and one for me.
Smoked salmon,
that is your favourite, isn't it?
How did you know that?
I'm gonna need a beer.
What, while we're working?
Oh, yeah, of course. Yeah, right.
Relax, kick back, it's a good idea.
Not for me, though, thanks.
Don't leave me, Jack.
You'll be okay.
-What was that all about?
-Temporary amnesia.
Owen's checking possible causes. Oh.
Weevil sighting by
the sewer in Rockall Street.
Jack?
-Can you see him?
-Who?
I'll drop you off
and check out the sighting.
I could come with you. It's been a while
since we went hunting together.
I'll be fine on my own.
(DOOR SLIDING SHUT)
Go on. Live a little.
(SIGHING) Well, as it's you.
Thank you.
-Call it a celebration!
-Oh, yes?
Adam and I have been together
for one year today.
Right, right.
A whole year.
My stomach still flips
when he touches me.
I've never known anything like it.
The two of us, we just fit.
-Do you know what I mean?
-Erm...
Not sure I do, no.
Oh, don't worry.
You'll meet the right girl one day.
Yeah. Tosh...
Erm...
Erm, do you really think
I look like a rodent?
Come on, we're going to crack this box
even if it kills us.
Come out, come out, wherever you are.
(GROWLING)
Giving me the run around, huh?
You picked the wrong day, my friend.
Get out! Get out, son.
-Dad?
-Run!
Jack? Was it down there? The Weevil?
No.
(THUNDER RUMBLING)
How did you get here?
I came with you Jack, remember?
Yeah, of course.
Are you okay?
Jack, what did you see?
My past.
-If what you say is true...
-It is.
We love each other.
But how could I forget that?
Nothing in.
I was going to take you out for a meal.
(POURING A DRINK)
Didn't want the weekend
to finish, I suppose.
Jack, please. Talk to me.
What about the past?
Is it your childhood?
I've always been here for you, Jack.
From the very beginning. I'm the one
you can confide in, remember?
It was meant to be buried.
I buried the memory over 150 years ago.
Why now?
Well, maybe it's time.
Maybe up till now, your subconscious
was protecting you.
But you can't block out
the past forever.
I can't afford to remember.
-Jack, talk to me, please.
-Why?
-I can help, trust me.
-I'm not sure I should do this.
Just tell me what you see.
I can help you. That's why I'm here.
Where are you, Jack?
Boeshane Peninsula.
My home in the 51 st century.
We lived under the threat of invasion.
They came without warning.
We thought they'd pass over us,
like they always did.
But they didn't.
-Not that day.
-Who?
The most horrible creatures
you could ever possibly imagine.
Their howls travelled before them.
Run! Take Gray. Keep him safe!
Take Gray.
Gray?
My little brother.
No, no, Dad. Come with us.
No, I've got to go get your mother. Run!
One minute I was holding his hand.
I don't know when he let go.
Gray? Gray!
Gray!
Gray, where are you? Gray!
One minute his hand was in mine,
I don't know when he let go. I...
I don't think I noticed.
I thought he was there, just behind me.
Gray!
(WEEPING) I retraced my steps.
Hoping that I'd see him again.
Did you find him?
Gray!
I ran all the way home.
Where are you, Gray?
Jack, what did you find?
Dad?
No!
Can someone help? Please!
I searched for Gray for years.
-I never found the body.
-It wasn't your fault.
I let go of his hand!
It was the worst day of my life.
It's the last thing I want to remember.
So, according to
the molecular breakdown,
this potentially alien complex artefact
is, in fact, made out of wood.
Well, perhaps it fell in the crate
by mistake.
Picked up meson energy
from the other stuff.
Yeah, right.
Oh, yes, sorry, it's a stupid idea.
I thinkJack brought it in.
No, I'm sure Adam found it on
an excavation a few months back.
I'll have a look in the diary.
I like to log the interesting stuff.
You write about artefacts in your diary?
Among other things.
So, we are done for the night.
I guess.
Everything all right?
Yeah. Just Adam hasn't rung yet.
Ah.
Sure he will.
I know I would.
If it was our anniversary.
(CHUCKLING NERVOUSLY)
I wouldn't disappear.
In fact, I would, cherish you.
-Ah, Owen.
-Yeah, no, no, really, really I would.
In fact, I wouldn't let you
out of my sight, Tosh.
Because I love you.
What?
Yeah, there we are.
I've said it. I love you!
Yes, I always have, actually,
ever since we
started working together
and, in fact, I actually ache for you.
Physically, when you're in the room, I
just want to reach out and touch you...
-Owen.
-No, no.
I can't keep this secret any more.
My mum said to me,
"Seize the day," and so I am seizing it
and, you know, I've got
so much love to give you, Tosh,
and, you know, you wouldn't know that
unless I tell you.
So here I am,
telling you that I love you.
You know, I know there's Adam,
okay, but I think,
in fact, I know that we would be
amazing together.
If you would only just give it a chance.
Oh, God.
Say something.
That is completely inappropriate.
-Pardon?
-What are you thinking of?
-I'm sorry, I just wanted you to know...
-How dare you!
I'm with Adam.
And even if I wasn't,
you're not my type, never will be.
Oh.
-Maybe I should be on my own tonight.
-No way.
-What if you forget who you are?
-I know who I am.
It's not just you who's lost something.
-But you remember.
-All you know about me.
You're my girl, my best friend.
(CASHIER CHATTERING ON PHONE)
Suddenly, all that's gone.
-CASHIER: What about her, mate?
-Where's he going now?
He just walked off!
He knows I'm waiting.
Oh, fine. I'll help myself, then!
Here you are, keep the change.
Buy some spot cream.
I'm not coming here again.
It's overpriced.
There's a £1.50 charge
on the cash machine.
It's a bloody disgrace.
Honestly, kids these days.
Don't know the meaning of hard work.
-What?
-Rhys the rant!
Always when you're in a queue
or driving,
or when you're on the phone to one
of those automated phone thingies.
Hey, it's okay. It's okay.
Come on, sweetheart.
What's wrong?
My diary.
You're not in it.
Everyone else is.
Why would I leave you out
when you've been here so long?
Like I'm remembering
a man who doesn't exist.
What are you?
Cross me and I will fill you
full of fake memories
until your head is on fire,
because that's how I exist.
Gwen. What did you do to her?
Memory's a very delicate thing.
Feeding myself in,
wiped other memories out.
It's a side effect of what
I have to do in order to survive.
Jack has to know!
Remember this.
ADAM: I know you didn't mean
to kill her,
you just couldn't stop yourself.
Remember this.
-I didn't do that.
-Oh, yes, you did.
And she wasn't the first.
ADAM: Good old Ianto, loyal Ianto.
Roaming the streets at night for bait.
My diary!
All human record is a lie. You twist it
into what you want to believe.
But we know the rot in your heart.
You crave flesh.
-No. Please!
-Remember it.
(YELLING)
Remember it.
Remember it! Remember it! Remember it.
(SCREAMING)
I help you dump the bodies.
It's me you call.
You know, I forgot what a rush it is,
feeding in the bad stuff.
(WHIMPERING)
Franklin? Franklin, wake up.
(WEEPING)
-Please.
-Mom?
Where's Gray? Where's Gray?
Where is he, son? Where is he?
We were running so fast.
One moment his hand was in mine.
No, not my little boy.
Not my little boy.
Why now?
Anything?
It's still a bit of a blur
but I'm getting there.
That's all we've got really. Memories.
That's what brought us to here.
To this point.
We found it before, we'll find it again.
You know, I...
I always worried that you'd...
That you'd just settled for me,
you know.
'Cause if you met me now, Gwen,
with all that goes on in your life,
could be that you wouldn't look
twice at me.
Don't say that.
-Do you remember that?
-No.
It felt like the first time.
But it was nice.
-I like that.
-I know.
Remind me some more.
IANTO: Jack!
Ianto.
Hey!
What's wrong?
You have to put me in the vaults.
Lock me up. I killed three girls.
-Strangled them.
-Stop kidding around.
I'm serious.
I murdered them in cold blood.
I took their bodies...
You have to lock me away.
Before I turn on you!
None of you are safe.
Hey, hey, come here, come here.
What's happened to you?
I'm a monster.
Best lie detector on the planet.
If something's untrue,
the light turns red.
Go.
My
hands on her throat.
And it felt so good.
Squeezing the life out of her.
It reads as truth.
I don't believe it.
Okay, tell me about the second girl.
(WHIMPERING)
She tried to get away,
but I was too quick.
Pleading
and I...
I didn't care.
Something in me wants to kill.
No.
This is not you.
Something's changed you.
You're not a murderer.
I'm certain of it.
ADAM: All human record is a lie.
You crave flesh. Remember this.
(IANTO SCREAMING)
A year ago today. Do you remember that?
Do you remember that?
Who the hell is this?
Just 'cause that's what I said
to you on your first day, remember?
Remember? Remember?
Well, I came with you Jack, remember?
Remember. Remember.
ADAM: I can help you.
That's why I'm here.
Remember this.
JACK: Come here, come here.
Just look, look.
Remember it.
(IANTO SCREAMING)
Remember it. Remember it. Remember it.
Remember it.
Where's Adam's blood sample?
-Everything's in order here.
-When was it last updated?
Twenty four hours ago.
(ADAM AND TOSHIKO CHATTERING)
Oh!
-Owen.
-About last night, it was selfish of me.
-Owen, I think the world of you.
-I know. I'm really sorry.
I just don't want to
jeopardise our friendship.
The most important thing
is that you're happy.
Thank you.
Tosh...
You are... You are happy with Adam,
aren't you?
-Completely.
-Okay.
-Hey.
-Hey, how are you today?
Erm, things are coming back slowly.
Rhys thought I shouldn't come
into work but...
Hey, we'll look after you.
You just have to give yourself time.
Come on, group hug.
(GIGGLING)
Hey, Ianto, come here.
You all right, mate?
Listen, I could murder a coffee.
Talk to me, Adam.
If that's even your name.
-What?
-What are you doing, Jack?
He's not who you think he is.
He's been feeding himself
into our memories by touch.
-Is this some kind of sick joke?
-He didn't exist until two days ago.
Can somebody tell me
what's going on here, please?
Jack, we've known him for years.
He's part of the team.
-No. He just made you think that.
-Come on, Jack.
Ah, you don't get to me like that.
Jack, you know me.
You recruited me three years ago.
All I know is that when
I think of my team, I see you there.
But I don't feel anything for you.
No pride, no warmth.
You, the one who I can confide in,
the one who unburied the dead.
Jack, maybe you've just forgotten him,
like I did with Rhys, yeah?
I should have spotted it then.
That wasn't stress, that was him.
By making us think we know him,
he disturbs our real memories.
I have no idea
what you are talking about.
-I'm taking him to the vaults.
-Jack, this is ridiculous.
JACK: Move!
-No!
-Tosh, that's not gonna help.
It's fine.
I'm just going to lock him up.
-Let him go.
-I'm not going to harm him.
-Why should I believe you?
-Tosh, Tosh, we can talk about this.
Drop the gun, Jack.
Get off me!
This is what you've done to us. Move!
Adam!
Don't kill me. I had to become part
of your memories in order to survive.
-I didn't mean any harm.
-You changed us.
For the better! You didn't remember
who you were. I helped you.
Look at Owen, all his cynicism gone.
He's a different man now.
Selfless, happier.
And Toshiko, too.
She's never been this confident.
How did you come here? Why us?
All of you have such unique memories.
Especially you, Jack.
All those extraordinary memories
you hold. Some hidden, some absent.
Your singular mind.
That's what drew me here.
Good job. It's what we do best.
Wipe out aliens.
You can't shoot me. You made me live!
And you always remember what you killed.
Don't you, Jack?
Our memories define us.
Adam changed those memories.
Changed who we are.
Now I have to help you all go back.
Find a memory that defines you.
Rediscover who you are.
If I'm wrong, he'll still be here
when we've done this.
Let me take you back
to before we all met.
Feel around for anything
that makes you what you are.
The hidden and the forgotten.
Tell me where you are.
GWEN: The college canteen.
Rhys is sitting opposite me,
telling stupid jokes.
RHYS: Where do you find a tortoise
with no legs?
Where you left it.
OWEN: It's my birthday. I'm ten.
Mum spends the whole day screaming.
"I love you because you're my son."
"But that doesn't mean
I have to like you."
TOSHIKO: Maths club.
Something so reliable about maths.
TOSHIKO: Always the right answer.
IANTO: Meeting Lisa.
Falling in love.
Never felt so alive.
OWEN: I turn 16. She packs my bags.
That is the nicest thing
you've done for me in years, Mother.
GWEN: Kissing him in the supermarket.
The look on his face.
TOSHIKO: My first flat.
I don't have a flat warming.
There's no one I want to invite.
IANTO: Losing Lisa.
Like the world had ended.
GWEN: The way he looks at me sometimes.
As if he's scared of what he feels
for me.
I love him.
But not in the way I love you.
Take this.
TOSHIKO: Knowing there has to be more
to life than this.
Knowing I'm special.
Waiting for someone to see it.
I saw it.
(PILL DROPPING)
OWEN: You save one life, 100 lives,
but it's never enough.
Who'll save me?
I will.
IANTO: Coming here...
It gave me meaning again.
You.
You each have a short term amnesia pill,
it'll make you forget Adam.
We have to wipe out the last
48 hours from our memories.
Go back to who we were.
(PANTING)
I'm going to lose so much.
JACK: None of it was real.
He loved me. And I loved him.
It's no different from real memory.
He forced it on you.
You have to let it go.
(SNIFFLING)
Goodbye, Adam.
Just me left.
Jack, I know what it's like
not to exist.
-Please, don't send me back there.
-I have to.
What are you going to do?
This will wipe out the past two days.
Well, you'll still keep
the bad memories.
Because they were always yours.
But what about the good times, Jack?
What about the last good
memory of you and your dad.
-It's lost.
-I can help you find it.
I can take you back there before I die.
-Why would you do that?
-I was in the void for so long.
The colours of this world
almost blinded me, Jack.
It was so beautiful after the darkness
and the stench of fear.
You gave me that.
Let me do this for you.
Come on, you want this.
It's early evening...
Just me and Dad.
(CHUCKLING)
-Oh, no you don't.
-You're out!
Ah!
You know, one day, you're not gonna want
to play with your old dad any more.
Never.
-Are you there?
-Yeah.
Me, Dad and...
-Dad! Mom said I could play, too.
-...Gray.
Hey, Gray!
-All right, son. One more.
-Okay.
Whoa, I'll get it.
I'm running for the ball.
Some other boy is there.
I don't know him.
-Can I play?
-Who are you?
My name's Adam.
Let me play. Before it gets dark.
There's lots of room.
FATHER: Hey, what are you doing?
-Are you all right?
-I just want to play.
-He can play.
-No.
He doesn't belong here.
I don't want him playing with us.
-I'm Adam.
-Don't touch my dad.
Hey, easy. Are you all right, Adam?
Yes, he just doesn't want to share.
Right, well, if you're going to behave
that way, we're going home.
No. What...
-Come on, Gray.
-No!
We don't leave yet.
We play some more, it gets dark.
We light a fire. Mom joins us.
Come on, son. I'll race you.
Race you.
Dad!
You did this. You spoiled it.
I made it happen.
JACK: Dad! Dad!
I love you.
Dad, Gray! Dad!
I want the real memory back.
Then let me live.
That box you found contains
my last good memory.
Of you, your dad and Gray.
You see, I'm a part of it now
and I'll always live
as long as you remember it.
That's why you took me back?
Wasn't it lovely? Playing in the sand,
no one knowing what was ahead.
Your dad laughing. Gray, safe and happy.
I don't want to die.
You take that pill and you will lose
everything I've given you.
Wipe me out now
and you will lose
all your memories of your father.
He will cease to have existed for you.
Goodbye, Adam.
Dad! Gray!
Come back! It wasn't like this!
Jack, how have we lost two days?
-What do you mean?
-IANTO: Lost 48 hours.
None of us can remember a thing.
The system's blank,
the CCTV's been wiped.
What's been going on?
What've we been doing?
I don't know.
Great. That's two days of my life
that I'll never get back!
Looks like Toshiko got herself
a secret admirer, though.
Oh, yeah?
To Tosh, love and apologies, Owen.
They're from you!
In your dreams, Tosh! I think
somebody's winding you up, darling.
No, I don't do flowers.
And I definitely don't do apologies.
-Did you call?
-Found your diary.
Yep, been looking for that.
And for the record,
measuring tapes never lie.
-Hey!
-Yep?
Who's Adam?
Don't know.
JACK: We've got a murder victim
and a survivor.
Both attacked with hypodermics,
both with their medical records wiped.
OWEN: My money's on this stuff
from Marie's blood.
-I had HIV.
-That's impossible.
OWEN: She's so normal, she's abnormal.
We're on the edge
of the greatest discovery in history.
That's got to be worth a few sacrifices.
JACK: We're not dealing with a freak
with a needle fetish.
This is a conspiracy.
OWEN: It's like the body's been turned
back to its factory settings.
JACK: An alien life form is preying
on the human bloodstream.
That's preposterous.
I need a way in there.
JACK: Miss Martha Jones.